Paul K. Perry Papers 2010.0028
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Paul K. Perry Papers
undated, 1920-1987
2010.0028
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
53.3 Linear feet
The collection contains correspondence, reports, studies, polls and similar materials related to the personal and professional interests of Paul K. Perry. Perry worked for the Gallup organization for a number of years and helped expand the organization.
Perry, Paul K.
Biography
Paul Keely Perry was born on February 22, 1910, in Camden, New Jersey, and grew up in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and Rochester, New York. He graduated from Tufts University in 1933.
Perry joined the American Institute of Public Opinion in 1935 not long after it was founded by George Gallup. The next year it made history not only by predicting correctly that Franklin Roosevelt would defeat Alf Landon but also by estimating the magnitude of the error the Literary Digest would make in its final release before the 1936 election.
In 1942 Perry moved to Audience Research, Inc., a Gallup affiliate, where he pioneered a multivariate approach for calculating the expected gross revenue of a motion picture. It was based on surveys regarding the public’s awareness of and interest in the film, its marquee appeal, and audience enjoyment as measured with the then new Hopkins Televote meters used by viewers to register their impressions of what they saw on the screen.
A turning point in Perry’s career came in the wake of the failure of the polls to anticipate the last-minute surge of support for Harry Truman in 1948. Even though he was still at Audience Research, Perry was asked by George Gallup to set up a system for the upcoming Congressional elections in 1950 that would pick up any late shifts in voter sentiment. Perry had always regarded the preelection poll as one of the most rigorous tests of the survey method and rose to the challenge.
To capture late trends and identify likely voters, Perry developed a design that included a pair of matching surveys within selected precincts. The first survey was conducted in the first week of October; field work for the second wrapped up the Friday of the week before the election. Results from the second survey were telegraphed to the Princeton offices of the Gallup Poll. The studies were comparable in terms of selected precincts but were not panel studies. Perry also devised a turnout scale based on several questions relating to voter participation.
Gallup was impressed with the rigor of Perry’s design and analysis and approved release to subscribing newspapers of a projection that the national vote for Congress would divide 51 percent Democratic and 49 percent Republican. Gallup also approved Perry’s recommendation that the release include the projection of a 28-seat gain for the Republicans. Perry based this projection on his analysis of regional shifts in voting intentions. Once the votes had been counted, Perry’s estimate of the division of the national vote was off by less than a percentage point, and his 28-seat figure was exactly on target.
Rather than rest on his laurels after the election, Perry turned immediately to a postmortem to validate the relative predictive value of the turnout questions that had been used by checking precinct records to determine which respondents had actually voted.
After serving as vice president of Audience Research and chief statistician of the Gallup Poll, Perry became president of the Gallup Organization in 1958. His new responsibilities did not diminish his efforts to improve preelection polling methods. He continued to explore one issue after another. He tested alternative ways of asking the candidate preference question. He experimented with split samples to shed light on whether respondents who marked “secret” ballots were less likely to be undecided than those who told interviewers which candidate, if any, they supported. He then used the difference to determine how to allocate undecided respondents in the final preelection poll. He designed procedures to integrate data from the last preelection survey and results from the more comprehensive early October survey. This made it possible to check for changing voter preferences while retaining a basis for robust estimation of likely turnout and an election’s probable outcome. And as noted, he continued postelection validation studies to gauge the efficacy of different questions and approaches in scaling respondents’ likelihood of voting.
What is noteworthy is that as he blazed a trail, he left markers for those who have followed. Perry was very forthcoming about the procedures he was developing. His articles in Public Opinion Quarterly went into considerable detail about sample design, turnout estimation, timing of surveys, allocation of undecided respondents, and use of the secret ballot.
In this same spirit, Perry was the featured speaker when George Gallup invited directors of state polls to Princeton the day before the 1951 American Association for Public Opinion Research (AAPOR) meeting. Mervin Field of the California Poll recalls this as the first of several “Local Pollers Conferences” that sprang from the openness of Gallup and Perry about the work they were doing. It imbued in him and others attending a sense of the importance of sharing developments with colleagues that would advance the cause of all polling.
Perry was responsible for all Gallup preelection polls from 1950 through 1976. Over the years Perry also oversaw dozens of non-election studies. One that particularly engaged his considerable imagination was the collaboration with the National Opinion Research Center on what would become Samuel Stouffer’s classic, Communism, Conformity, and Civil Liberties (1955).
Perry is remembered for his generosity and quiet manner. He spoke often of all he learned from others and the confidence with which he could turn projects over to associates at the Gallup Organization, particularly his longtime deputy and close friend, the late Irving Crespi. Those who worked with Perry reciprocated by striving to meet the high standards he set—especially for himself.
Perry’s contributions provide ample evidence that there is nothing so practical as a theory if it is applied with care and that nothing advances a theory so much as putting it to the test in the real world.
Paul Perry passed away April 7, 2005 at the age of 95.
Scope and Contents
The Paul K. Perry Papers contain correspondence, reports, manuscripts, and articles pertaining to Perry's area of expertise in election polling and his relationship and responsibilities with the Gallup Organization. Many of the materials inluded are related to congressional and presidential elections, from the mid to late twentieth century, and the numerous individuals associated with them. The collection also includes publications, clippings, ephemera, and notes related to Gallup polling as well as his memoirs [176 MB, PDF]. Among the subjects discussed in the collection are Audience Research Inc., the European Society for Opinion and Marketing Research, the Institute for Social Research at the University of Michigan, The Joint Center for Political Studies, and public opinion reporters. The papers also contain publications from the Atlantic Monthly and the Montgomery Advertiser, and contain various publciations related to the Gallup Organization, to include Computation of Descriptive Statistics by Jack W. Dunlap, and Increasing Profits with Continuous Audience Research, Dr. George H. Gallup. The collection is comprosed of materials from before the period that Perry began working for the Gallup Organization.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to politics and publications, public polling and survey research. See especially the Papers of James Vicary, Samuel Lubell, Warren Mitofsky, Daniel Yankelovich, and Archibald Crossley. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Provenance and Acquisition
The papers were donated in 2009 by Paul G. Perry, Mark W. Perry, Ruthmarie P. Thomas, and Alice P. Strong.
Public opinion--United States.; Public polling collections
- Series I: An Inventory, undated, 1920-1987
  - Research materials (reprints, articles, reports, data, studies, notes, Gallup Organization materials), undated, 1959-1980 (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include: Survey November Elections, 1980; Semantic Differential Applied to Image Research, undated; Analysis of Variance, undated, 1961; Measure of association labeled “gamma,” undated; Notes re: Schmidt’s Beer Study (#0051), undated; Papers written by others, undated; Sampling papers and notes, undated; Bill Allen, undated; Cluster Analysis, undated; Rank correlation, undated; Taxonomy, 1959-1971; Correspondence, minutes and financial records pertaining to the Gallup Organization, undated, 1970s-1980s; Power Tables for the t-test, undated; Statistical papers, 1962-1963; Factor analysis, undated; Chi square, undated Attitudes, verbal behavior and other behavior, 1966; Publications (Gallup and others), 1963-1965.]
  - Memoranda, notes, studies, reports, correspondence, articles, clippings, undated, 1952-1983 (Box 2)
    [Subjects include: Turnout-Percent voted 1950 to date (0001-E), 1982; Accuracy record, undated; Guttman (0026 E), 1952; Scalometer ratings of candidates (0025 E), undated; Papers and letters with reference to election survey methodology (0024 E), undated; Secret ballot and history of its adoption (0023 E), undated; Validation of voting participation (0022 E), undated; Report on registration and voting participation (0021 E), undated; Presidential vote by states 1952, 1956, 1960 (0020 E), undated; Which party will do the best job of keeping the country prosperous (0019 E), undated; Which party will keep us out of World War III, Trends (0018 E), undated; Effect of question order on present preference (0017 E), undated; Precinct standard deviation, 1952, 1956, 1960 (0016 E), undated; Precinct standard deviation using election data (0015 E), undated; Bill McPhee’s memo and letter (0014 E), 1954; ;Education Distribution among registered voters (0013 E), 1964; Comparison of ratio method and absolute method 1930-1960 (0012 E), undated; Undecided—Nonsecret 1950 to date (0011 E), undated; Tunrout scale weighting (0010 E), undated; Memo re state political surveys in 1960, evaluation of error (0009 E), 1976; Comparison of error with and without ratio adjustment 1950 to date (0005 E), undated; Comparison of voting preference of voters and non-voters in post election validation studies 1952 to date (0004 E), undated; Turnout comparison of pre-election preference among voters with pre-election preference of likely voters (0003 E), undated; Estimated standard error for samples with no. –or precincts used in indicated elections, etc. (0002 E), undated; Election memos (6607), 1966-1967; (6662) Computer printouts, undated Precinct sample I and II final and semi-final estimates (6625), undated; PSII-Post election analysis-regression estimate (6484), undated; Adjective list #697 (6431), 1965; PS I and II Congressional vote by turnout scores 0 through 8 (6238), undated; Turnout-Guttman scale analysis (6227), undated; Precinct sample II-post election analysis (6035), undated; Precinct sample II by turnout levels and by precincts #423 (5855), undated; Turnout scale-Presidential and Congressional PS I and II also secret vs non secret on 572 and 573 (5633), undated; 1954 Congressional, precinct sample, individual precinct results (5401), undated; Precinct sample-plan to vote and turnout scale (5218), undated; 1950 Congressional precinct sample, Education, sex, age, religion, size of family and total: survey I and II (5001), undated; Election materials (printouts), undated; Memo describing 1974 procedures for developing a final preelection estimate, 1976; Fulcrum (0027 E), undated; Turnout questions cross tabbed with precinct preference (6873), undated; 1968 presidential memo, 1980; Descriptive memo concerning 1972, 1980; 1972 presidential memo, 1980; 1976 election memos, 1976; 1976 Congressional trend memo, 1977 1976 data, undated; 1978 election memos, 1979; 1978 Congressional memos, 1977; 1979 memos-PKP letters, undated, 1979; Election survey methods, 1972 revision; Releases, Gallup Poll, 1980-1981; Gallup Organization balance sheets, profit/loss statements, 1981-1984; Stock agreements, 1971-1979; Pension memos, 1979-1980; Memos re: financial arrangements with Gallup Organization, 1980; Conference notes, 1980; Memos and letters issued, 1979-1981; Public Opinion Quarterly, Childs, Harold L., 1968; Bean, Louis H., 1973-1974; Cantril, Hadley, 1955-1967; Singer, Eleanor, 1978-1981; Finch-Nixon memo, 1960; Talk to local AAPOR chapter 1981 October 27; Kann, Peter, 1972-1984; Tibby, Jack, 1980; Thursday am meeting notes, undated; Memo re: actual errors vs. theoretical error in 10 state election surveys in 1960. Done for Claude Robinson for Nixon, 1964; Kann, Robert A., 1958, 1984; Robinson, Claude, 1958; Preferences, 1979; Correspondence, 1982; Correspondence— Gallup Organization, 1959; Correspondence— Gallup Organization, 1946-1958; Correspondence— Gallup Organization,1960; Congressional, 1981-1982; Frankel, Jesse J., 1969; Freedman, David, 1977; Goodell, Senator Charles E., 1971; Roper, Burns, 1977-1986; Da Costa, Eri c, 1970; Sheatsley, Paul, 1983; Crespi. Irving, 1983; Morgan, Roy, 1985; Kagay, Mike, undated; British Gallup, 1982; Letters and memos, George H. Gallup, 1983.]
  - Reports, studies, correspondence, publications, data, clippings, reviews, financial recrods, reprints, off prints, clippings, notes, undated, 1920-1983 (Box 3)
    [Subjects include: Correspondence; AAPOR award; conference materials; Gallup Organization balance sheets, profit/loss statements; Report—sample for Reports 8 and 9 of the Continuing Study of Magazine Audiences; Regression estimate (8006); New York Motion Picture market study; Review of “Reflections on Political Polling in Jamaica;” Review of “Using early returns for prediction in primary elections;” Work in preparation for final estimate.]
  - Notecards, correspondence, articles, memoranda, reports, surveys, 195901980 (Box 4)
    [Subjects include: Dr. Gallup; “Election survey methods and a review of the 1964 situation;” “Determinants of the outcome of midterm congressional elections;” “Impact of Chappaquiddick on the Kennedy candidacy;” Review; Analysis; Congressional; Gallup organization year end reviews; New Jersey opinion study; “Demography of the 1970s;” “Proposal for a national study of citizen knowledge and perceptions of the US House of Representatives;” “Mixed changes in consumer confidence;” Gallup reports; Post election validation summary; Guttman scales; Ludwig and FOA; “Sources of the shift to political independence;” 1976 elections; Irving Crespi reprints; Validation deck; Conference materials ( India, Germany); Gallup home electronic brand index; W. Edwards Deming reprint; John Davies attempt to misrepresent his role; “Attitudes toward readership of the Merck Review;” “Researching the future;” “Some Observations on social indicators and marketing decisions;" “Polls and the political process;” AAPOR award; “Comparison of three rating scales.” ]
  - Clippings, articles, notes, studies, speeches, publications, undated, 1947-1990s (Box 5)
    [Subjects include: Seat Projection, Multivariate analysis, Elections, New York survey, Gallup Organization, World Association for Public Opinion, Audience research.]
  - Publications, memoranda, reports, notes, correspondence, clippings, articles, programs, press releases, survey data, 1930s-1984 (Box 6)
    [Subjects include: “Reforming the presidential nominating process,” Irving Crespi, W. Edwards Deming, Gallup, “Brief history of the motion picture research activities of Audience Research, Inc.,” “Current public attitudes toward business ethics,” “Waukegan study of voter turnout predictions” Miller, “Reply to request for proposal—FEA141: research to evaluate the effectiveness of public conservation-oriented communication,” Interviewer’s instruction manual, “Analysis telephone v. personal survey results,” “Gallup Organization, Inc. Corporate Headquarter feasibility report,” “Presidential candidate trial-heats, 1936-1980,” “Evaluation of a sampling system employed by the Performing Rights Organization of Canada, Ltd.,” “Some lessons of 40 years of election surveying with the Gallup Poll” 1977 3 cs. “Political Polls and pollsters” Burke, “Anatomy of a Carter victory,” “Turn out scale,” George Gallup, Jr.’s letter to the Packet, “Trial heats Nixon, Rockefeller, Humphrey and Wallace,” Gallup organization materials (memoranda, reports, survey data, reports, studies, questionnaires), “Identification of Bank advertising slogans,” “Report on Survey I Among aluminum fabricators,” “Report on Survey I Among business leaders,” “Report on Survey I Among financial analysts,” “Report on Survey I Among US adults.”]
  - Publications, correspondence, clippings, notes, articles, contracts, manuals, 1930-1973 (Box 7)
    [Subjects include: “Turnout problem in election surveys,” “Attitudes of visitors to the Guggenheim museum,” “Survey of business executives,” Study of non-voters, “Some lessons of 40 years of election surveying with the Gallup Poll,” “Marketing and attitude research applied to motion pictures,” “Proposal concerning a postal Life magazine readership survey,” Harvard Business Review, “Survey of the public concerning the National Parks,” “Intelligent interpretation and use of public opinion surveys,” “Election survey methods,” “Role of foreign affairs in the 1964 Presidential election,” Election data file.]
  - Clippings, notes, obituaries, publications, correspondence, reprints, 1950-1977 (Box 8)
    [Subjects include: “Report on the 1968 election,” “Comparison of alternative procedures for collecting consumer expenditure data for frequently purchased products,” Research materials, “Elements of electoral choice, 1952-1972,” “Measuring the effectiveness of combined media campaigns,” “Using consumer research to plan the launching of an unfamiliar and new product in the market—the case of avocado,” “Attitude components analysis,” “Reply to RFP-- FEA 141: Research to evaluate the effectiveness of public conservation –oriented communication,” “Proposal for a study to assess the needs of libraries in New Jersey,” “Multiple regression analysis: The relation between overtime worked in 1972 and attitude toward overtime,” Secret v non-secret research materials, Precinct sample and analysis, Turnout factor, Pinpoint memos, “Survey concerning cigarette smoking health check ups cancer detection tests,” “Proposal for a study to assess needs for and attitudes toward social services in New Jersey,” “Predicting voter turnout.”]
  - Research notes, clippings and articles, publications, references, undated, 1952-1982 (Box 9)
    [Subjects include: Comparisons of ballots, Conference notes, precinct Sample, Method and analysis prior to election, Precinct sample questionnaires, Standard error due to clustering notes, Post election validation, Precincts in which names obtained and check of whether resp. voted, Post election validation, Presidential Voter validation, Post election validation of voters/non voters, Annual meetings, Special Wallace tabulation.]
  - Research notes, cards and correspondence, undated (Box 10)
  - Publications, news releases, reviews, notes, memoranda, articles, research, clippings, manuscripts, undated, 1965-1980 (Box 11)
    [Subjects include: AAPOR Standards committee, “Study of public reaction to the motion picture ’To Sir, with love’,” Gallup Conference, “Role of foreign affairs in the 1964 Presidential election,” “Attitudes concerning racial violence and the war in Vietnam and a measure of confidence in the political leadership to deal with these problems,” “Public Opinion Studies in the US,” Princeton Jewish Center, Election survey materials, “Consumer reactions to the 1961 Lincoln continental,” Ration and regression estimates, GIRI, "Interviewer procedures for precinct sample ‘76,” Materials for talk on Sample.]
  - Publications (serials, clippings), undated (Box 12)
  - Books, undated (Box 13)
  - Publications (serials), undated (Box 14)
  - References, clippings, reports, notes, memoranda, correspondence, manuscripts, undated, 1952-1974 (Box 15)
    [Subjects include: “Survey of consumer attitudes and beliefs concerning gasoline and brands of gasoline,” “Certain problems in Election survey methodology,” Turnout scale, Correlation between Kennedy 1960 election and Johnson 1964 by precincts, Sampling, “Two county Buffalo Beer market,” “Public attitudes towards certain current social problems,” “Political Notebook,” 1968 validation, Correlation between preference of party affiliation in 1968 and coefficient, “Problem of the Republican party" Design of the sample, “Survey of opinion among registered voters in Stockton, CA, on the 2 cent amusement tax” undated “Measurement of Candidate preferences and the role of issues in the 1968 presidential election,” George H. Gallup mss and notes, “Procedure for the creation of segments and the selection of respondents within households.”]
  - Newspaper clippings, photocopies, memoranda, manuscripts, correspondence, reports, studies, speeches, clippings, 1952-1984 (Box 16)
    [Subjects include: Turnout Scale valuations based on 1984 precinct sample data, Interviewer’s manual, Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan, Irving Crespi manuscripts, Election materials, Collected speeches of George Gallup, Report of findings from 1503 personal interviews, Estimates of standard error by total and by region using the Sterr program, Computation of 1952 presidential, sampling error, multiple regressions, Sampling error projections, Precinct correction factors by elections, Materials for precinct sample survey, Post election validation (related to folder in Box 9), W. Edwards Deming, Marketing and attitude research, Public opinon studies in the US, “What bearing does the failure of the pollsters to predict Truman’s election to the presidency have on the validity of opinion and attitude surveys in market Research?,” “Election Survey methods,” “Comparison of the voting preferences of likely voters and likely nonvoters,” Gallup poll plans for the 1956 presidential election.]
  - Publications, undated (Box 17)
  - Notes, agenda, clippings, reports, studies, memoranda, correspondence, financial records, questionnaires, photographs, photocopies, 1950-1980 (Box 18)
    [Subjects include: I. Crespi, Survey research and the 1964 election, Structural basis for right wing conservatism in the US, Historical election materials, State of mankind pre-test, Interviewer influence, Presidential preference by turnout scale and education jointly, National survey on drug abuse, Forcasting business trends, Report of findings from 1555 personal interviews, Review of the 1950 “Pinpoint” operation, 1950 Congressional Turnout, POQ article secret v. non secret analysis by elections, “Assessment of public opinion data sets,” “Presidential Campaign,” “Public attitudes toward Richard Nixon as a political personality,” “Political attitudes of new voters for the 1972 presidential election,” “How to end US participation in the fighting in Vietnam,” Gallup organization, “ Roy Morgan, the Gallup Poll man.”]
  - Notes, memoranda, reports, presentations, photocopies, clippings, articles, surveys, analysis, correspondence, questionnaires, studies, manuscripts, speeches, undated, 1941-2004 (Box 19)